Guide to the Lois Mulkearn Research Files, 1937-1956 DAR.1981.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Lois Mulkearn Research Files
1937-1956
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Mulkearn, Lois
DAR.1981.01
1.67 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The collection consists of manuscript drafts, topic notes, transcripts, and correspondence collected by Lois Mulkearn, the first librarian at the University of Pittsburgh's Darlington Memorial Library and a historian. Mulkearn authored and co-authored a number of books about Western Pennsylvania history, including A Traveler's Guide to Historic Western Pennsylvania. This collection contains manuscript drafts and topic notes associated with the book. Also included are transcripts of court cases involving various parties and George Mason of the Ohio Company dating from 1743 to 1763. The cases mostly pertain to debts owed to the Ohio Company by various men and women. Additionally, there are notes related to industrial hygiene and safety during the late eighteenth to mid twentieth centuries which are associated with an unknown publication or lecture and drafts of essays written by Mulkearn.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection consists of manuscript drafts, topic notes, transcripts, and correspondence collected by Lois Mulkearn, the first librarian at the University of Pittsburgh's Darlington Memorial Library. A portion of the materials is related to the book A Traveler's Guide to Historic Western Pennsylvania, written by Lois Mulkearn and Edwin V. Pugh and published by the University of Pittsburgh Press in 1954. The notes and manuscript drafts for the book are arranged by topics relating to the subject of the book, namely histories of various locations in Western Pennsylvania.
Additional materials consist of transcripts of court cases involving George Mason of the Ohio Company, which was founded in 1747 and represented the trading and land prospecting interests of a handful of Virginia planters, and settlers who were in debt to the company. The cases are listed in alphabetical order by the last name of the party involved and date from between 1751 to 1763. It is possible these transcripts were used in Mulkearn's book George Mercer Papers, the authoritative volume on the Ohio Company published by the University of Pittsburgh Press in 1954.
Other materials in the collection consist of notes about industrial safety and hygiene during the late eighteenth to mid twentieth centuries prepared for an unknown lecture or publication and drafts of Mulkearn's essays on a variety of historic topics.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lois Mitsch, niece of Lois Mulkearn, to the Darlington Memorial Library in 1981.
Custodial History
This collection was located in the Darlington Memorial Library in the University's Cathedral of Learning until 2007 when it was moved to the ULS Archives Service Center for processing, storage, preservation and service. However, it remains in the custodianship of the ULS Special Collections Department.
Previous Citation
Lois Mulkearn Research Files, 1937-1956, DAR.1981.01, Darlington Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Bibliography
Mulkearn, Lois, and Edwin V. Pugh. A Traveler's Guide to Historic Western Pennsylvania. [Pittsburgh]: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1954.
Mercer, George, and Lois Mulkearn. George Mercer Papers Relating to the Ohio Company of Virginia. [Pittsburgh]: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1954.
Armstrong County (Pa.); Allegheny County (Pa.); Pennsylvania -- Description and travel; Washington County (Pa.); Crawford County (Pa.); Elk County (Pa.); Erie County (Pa.); Westmoreland County (Pa.); Forest County (Pa.); Indiana County (Pa.); Jefferson County (Pa.); Lawrence County (Pa.); McKean County (Pa.); Fayette County (Pa.); Mercer County (Pa.); Potter County (Pa.); Cambria County (Pa.); Somerset County (Pa.); Greene County (Pa.); Bedford County (Pa.); Correspondence; Transcripts; Manuscripts (Document genre); Warren County (Pa.); Venango County (Pa.); Clearfield County (Pa.); Ohio River Valley -- History -- Sources; Clarion County (Pa.); Cameron County (Pa.); Pennsylvania -- History, Local; Butler County (Pa.); Blair County (Pa.); Beaver County (Pa.); Mason, George; Mulkearn, Lois; Ohio Company (1747-1779); Pugh, Edwin V.; University of Pittsburgh. Press; University of Pittsburgh
- Counties in Western Pennsylvania Research Notes, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series consists of notes describing the locations and histories of counties in Western Pennsylvania. The information is grouped by specific counties, and includes correspondence between Mulkearn and historians from county governments and historical societies. The time period covered is the mid-nineteenth to early twentieth centuries. In many cases, the information is divided by locations Mulkearn and Pugh included in A Traveler's Guide to Historic Western Pennsylvania.
  - Allegheny County (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Armstrong County (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Beaver County (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bedford County (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Butler County (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cambria County (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cameron County (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clarion County (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clearfield County (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Crawford County (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Erie County (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fayette County (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Greene County (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Indiana County (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jefferson County (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lawrence County (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mercer County (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Potter County (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Somerset County (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Venango County (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Warren County (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Westmoreland County (Box 1, Folder 22)
- A Traveler's Guide to Historic Western Pennsylvania Notes and Revisions, II.
  This series consists of research notes related to A Traveler's Guide to Historic Western Pennsylvania that detail historic locations within the city of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, and surrounding communities, including Sewickley and Fox Chapel. Notes are included about specific locations and historic events. There are also manuscript drafts from Mulkearn and Pugh's book with revisions and correspondence from local historians.
  - Location Research Notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript drafts and Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Ohio Company Court Cases, III.
  Series III consists of transcripts of court cases between George Mason, an agent of the Ohio Company, and parties owing debts to the Ohio Company. The cases date from 1750 to 1763. Examples of documents enclosed in the files include promissory notes and arrest warrants for the party in debt. The records are modern copies of court files created in Fredrick County, Virginia. They are arranged by the last name of the defendant involved.
  Other materials chronicle land surveys and court cases involving attempts of the Ohio Company to obtain land in Maryland, Virginia, and Ohio. It is possible these transcripts were used in Mulkearn's book George Mercer Papers Relating to the Ohio Company of Virginia, the authoritative volume on the Ohio Company.
  - Non-Ohio Company Court Cases, 1751-1763 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Thomas Bladen Land Surveys (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Castleman, William, October 28, 1751 - June 5, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Caton, Thomas, July 1750 - March 17, 1763 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chapman, Richard, March 20, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Coburn, Jonathan, October 21, 1751 - June 5, 1755 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Craig, David, January 15, 1750 - August 6, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cunningham, John, October 20, 1750 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Enochs, Enoch, August 11, 1750 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ervin, Robert, October 7, 1751 - March 20, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Findley, James, July 1750 - July 1753 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hood, James, June 1752 - September 14, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Houghland, Jacob, November 21, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ice, Frederick, December 17, 1751 - Nocember 9, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Jock, Jeremiah, June 29, 1750 - February 7, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Johnson, John, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Jones, John, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Lane, Edward (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Lane, Richard, December 11, 1752 - September 5, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lemen, Robert, July 6, 1752 - September 18, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Long, John Adam, July 6, 1752 - September 18, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - McDonough, Mark, January 15, 1750 - 1753 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - McFadden, John, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Martin, James, March 31, 1752 - June 6, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Mounts, Joseph, 1753 - 1754 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Mounts, Peter, February 7, 1759 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Mounts, Providence, June 8, 1751 - January 11, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Nicholas, John, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Nicholls, John, November 21, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Park, George, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Parker, Jr., George, 1754 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Patterson, William, August 24, 1751 - June 5, 1755 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Pearce, John, October 4, 1751 - February 2, 1757 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Richey, William, July 24, 1750 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Ross, Francis, March 11, 1753 - February 7, 1759 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Ross, James, 1751 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Ruth, Zacheus, May 24, 1750 - June 10, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Rutherford, Thomas, October 28, 1750 - January 3, 1758 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Shelby, Catherine, November 1752 - March 19, 1754 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Sutton, Jasper, July 27, 1751 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Swearingen, H.D., March 20, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Swearingen, Thomas, September 11, 1750 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Taylor, Samuel, August 4, 1750 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Teagarden, Abraham, July 17, 1751 - June 5, 1755 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Thacker, Amos, November 21, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Tomilson, Nathaniel, August 21, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Toster, Peter, August 3, 1750 - August 6, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Trowhawk, John, March 14, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Trucker, John, July 17, 1751 - June 5, 1755 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Volgamore, Joseph, August 21, 1753 - March 1754 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Walktaker, Conrad, June 16, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Williams, John, March 1752 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Williams, Remembrance, July 28, 1750 - June 8, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Wolf, Jacob, July 9, 1751 - June 5, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Wood, Jacob, August 8, 1751 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Wood, Thomas, August 3, 1750 - August 6, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Industrial Hygiene and Saftey Notes, IV.
  Series IV consists of notes about industrial safety and hygiene. The notes regarding industrial hygiene and safety focus on the working conditions of the steel industry in Pennsylvania. They are on index cards and appear to be for an unknown publication. Citations from different bibliographic sources are included. Some of the note cards are fastened together by subject. Most of the materials cited date from the early eighteenth to early twentieth centuries.
  - Industrial Hygiene and Saftey (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Industrial Hygiene and Saftey (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Industrial Hygiene and Saftey (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Mulkearn Drafts, Transcripts, and Journal, V.
  Series V consists of transcripts of works written by Mulkearn. Included is a transcript of a journal she kept while in Great Britain before the start of World War II. The works transcribed relate mostly to colonial Western Pennsylvania. On some transcriptions, handwritten notes and corrections to the text are included.
  - Mulkearn Drafts, Transcripts, and Journal (Box 4, Folder 4)